Finding aid for the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archive Collection of Audio Materials, 1970-1999 LSC.2230
UCLA Library Special Collections
June L. Mazer Lesbian Archive Collection of Audio Materials
1970 - 1999
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2230
6 linear feet (6 record cartons)
This collection consists of audio recordings from the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives. It captures the culture, diversity, politics, scholarship, and activism that the Mazer collected. The tapes reflect the activism that women were involved with in Los Angeles and California throughout the latter half of the twentieth century. The content of the material includes recordings of conferences, workshops, meetings, performances, radio broadcasts, interviews, and oral histories concerning topics such as homosexuality, women's health, politics, women in history, feminism, racism, discrimination, literature, and music. Recordings of Judy Grahn, Peg Crukshank, Judy Freespirit, June Mazer, Bunny MacCulloch, Del Martin, Phyllis Lyon, Kitty Tsai, Eloise Klein Healy, Anne Sexton, Lillian Faderman, Liz Maines and others can be found in the collection.
Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Audio materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Acquisition Information
Provenance unknown. This collection is part of an outreach and collection-building partnership between the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW) and the UCLA Library.
Historical Note
The June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives document this lives of lesbians and feminists in Southern California.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of audio recordings from the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives. It captures the culture, diversity, politics, scholarship, and activism that the Mazer collected. The tapes reflect the activism that women were involved with in Los Angeles and California throughout the latter half of the twentieth century. The content of the material includes recordings of conferences, workshops, meetings, performances, radio broadcasts, interviews, and oral histories concerning topics such as homosexuality, women's health, politics, women in history, feminism, racism, discrimination, literature, and music. Recordings of Judy Grahn, Peg Crukshank, Judy Freespirit, June Mazer, Bunny MacCulloch, Del Martin, Phyllis Lyon, Kitty Tsai, Eloise Klein Healy, Anne Sexton, Lillian Faderman, Liz Maines and others can be found in the collection.
- Forums/Talks Cassettes, 1973-1983; Series 16.; 51 audio cassette tapes
  Scope and Contents note
  Audio recordings of forums and scholarly talks on various lesbian and women's issues, including feminism in academics, gay and lesbian archives, lesbian sexual theory, lesbian fiction and poetry, religion, legal issues, disability, aging, parenting, and paternity issues. Speakers include Emily Culpepper, Lisa Ben, Bunny MacCulloch, Amber Hollibaugh, Lilian Faderman, Joan Nestle, Deborah Edle, Barbara Walters, Billie Jean King, Del Martin, Phyllis Lyon, Joanne Castillo, Peg Kruikshank, Jean Mountaingrove, Cherrie Moraga, Barbara Smith, Judge Mary Morgan, Lisa Rofel, Kathleen Weston, Rosemary Kurt, Nancy Manahan, and Judy Grahn.
  - Feminist Autonomy and Scholarship: Does It Exist?, 11 May 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 1)
    Speaker Emily Culpepper, a doctoral student at Harvard, presents her research at a lecture for the Women's and Feminist Studies departments at Stanford. Her issue is feminist autonomy and scholarships, asking the question what and how it exists. She explores how women are able to, and in what context, claims free mental space for independent scholarship in the academic world. Dr. Emily Erwin Culpepper is the founding Director of Women's Studies at the University of Redlands.
  - Lisa Ben: Crurising Down the Avenue, undated (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 2)
    The Spirit of Place. Rich lived from 1929 to 2010 and was an American poet, essayist, and feminist.
  - What We Roll in Bed With, 8 May 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 3-4)
    Recording of talk in San Francisco, CA, with speaker Amber Hollibaugh. She worked with the San Francisco Lesbian and Gay History Project and studies issues of sexuality and lesbian sexual theory. Hollibaugh's discussion centers around sexual issues, lesbianism, and the progressive Left. Hollibaugh is an American writer, film-maker, feminist, and political activist.
  - Surpassing the Love of Men, 17 September 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 5-6)
    Lillian Faderman reads from her previously published article, "The History of Lesbian Magazine Fiction in the Early 20th Century," and discusses literary history of lesbians. Faderman is a scholar who writes on the topics of lesbian relationships and romantic friendships in history.
  - Preserving Our Lesbian Heritage, 8 July 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 7-8)
    Recording of the Lesbian Herstory Archives forum and slideshow at the Women's Building in San Francisco, CA. The West Coast Lesbian Collections sponsored the event. The purpose of the event was to emphasize the importance of preserving lesbian movement history and encouraging community involvement. Representatives, Joan Nestle and Deborah Edel, from the New York Lesbian Herstory Archive present a slideshow.
  - Preserving Our Lesbian History, San Jose Showing, 12 July 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 9)
    Recording of the Lesbian Herstory Archives forum and slideshow in San Jose, CA. Included is the introduction and afterword presentation with Nikki, Lynn, and Johnie. The West Coast Lesbian Collections sponsored the event. The purpose of the event was to emphasize the importance of preserving lesbian movement history and encouraging community involvement. Representatives, Joan Nestle and Deborah Edel, from the New York Lesbian Herstory Archive present a slideshow.
  - Old Dykes Tales, 30 January 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 10-11)
    Recorded by the Lesbian Herstory Project in San Francisco. Speaker introduces the program and provides explanation of purpose of program. She discusses what being "Old Gay" means--being a lesbian before the women's movement of the late 1960s and 1970s--and the importance of storytelling. Audience members share stories of coming out, relationships, and notable events in their lives.
  - Billie Jean King Interview, 7 May 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 12)
    Recording of 60 Minutes interview with Billie Jean King. Barbara Walters interviewed King and the two discussed the "Marilyn Barnett Affair." King is an American former professional tennis player and an advocate for sexual equality in sports. She won the "Battle of the Sexes" tennis match against Bobby Riggs in 1973. King was forced to publicly acknowledge her sexual orientation after Barnett filed a palimony lawsuit against King.
  - The State of Lesbians in the 80s, 7 April 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 13)
    Speakers Phyllis Lyon and Del Martin speak and take questions on the state of the lesbian and feminist movement in the United States at the time. They discuss the progress that has been made, how society has changed, and what needs to happen for the movement to advance--including politics, religion, and other coinciding movements like the gay men's movement. Dorothy Louise Taliaferro "Del" Martin and Phyllis Ann Lyon were an American lesbian couple known as feminist and gay-rights activists. They were a couple until Del Martin's death on August 27, 2008
  - Lesbian Politics..., 25 March 1980; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 14)
    Phyllis Lyon, Del Martin, and Jose Saria speak at the Harvey Milk Demonstration Club in San Francisco, CA. Del Martin and Del Martin discuss their lives and times in San Francisco. Dorothy Louise Taliaferro "Del" Martin and Phyllis Ann Lyon were an American lesbian couple known as feminist and gay-rights activists. They were a couple until Del Martin's death on August 27, 2008
    General note
    Poor quality recording.
  - Recent Research in Lesbian History, 1 April 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 15)
    Joanne Castillo presents research on the recording and preservation of gay and lesbian history. Castillo explains the foundation behind the action to record the history of the lesbian movement, presents a review of published gay and lesbian history, and argues for greater preservation for the purpose of academic research and political action.
  - Lesbians in Denmark, [ca. 1980s]; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 16)
    English and Danish are spoken. Discussion on the history of and the current state of the lesbian and women's movement in Denmark.
    Audio quality is poor.
  - Trends in Lesbian Publishing, 13 January 1982; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 17)
    Talk featuring Peg Cruikshank at the Eureka Valley/ Harvey Milk Memorial Branch Library in San Francisco, CA. Cruikshank discusses the new field [at the time of talk] of lesbian publishing, which includes lesbian presses, lesbian writers, and lesbian and women's issues themes in writing.
  - Jean Mountaingrove, 4 September 2001; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 18)
    Recording of Jean Mountaingrove at OWL and Rootworks, including planning meetings, speeches, and interviews. Mountaingrove lived "off the grid" on women's land in Southern Oregon for 30 years. Her focus is on living close to nature and empowering herself and other women through creativity. She helped produce WomanSpirit, a magazine of feminist spirituality from 1974-84. She also co-hosted 15 years of annual Dyke Art Camp. Jean Mountaingrove and Ruth Mountaingrove established Rootworks in Sunny Valley, Oregon during the 1970s. The goal of Rootworks was to act as a lesbian separatist community.
  - Disabled and Abled, 29 November 1982; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 1-2)
    Operation Concern for Disabled Lesbians support group presentation. Topics discussed include the work the group has done with disable lesbians, lessons learned dialogue, and the general experiences created from their community. The group was run by Ricki Boden.
  - Third World Women's Publishing, 1 November 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 3-4)
    Cherrie Moraga and Barbara Smith present a discussion about women of color in publishing, including speaking about their work with Kitchen Table Press and reading published poetry. Cherríe L. Moraga is a Chicana writer, feminist activist, poet, essayist, and playwright. Moraga has taught courses in dramatic arts and writing at various universities across the United States and is an artist in residence at Stanford University. Barbara Smith is an American, lesbian feminist who has played a significant role in building and sustaining Black Feminism in the United States. Since the early 1970s she has been active as a critic, teacher, lecturer, author, scholar, and publisher of Black feminist thought.
  - History of Lesbians of Color, 1 June 1980; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 5-6)
    Panel on the topic of lesbians of color from history and the experience of minority women in the United States. Speakers share personal stories, as well as the stories of women from history, including M. Quintanales and Sojourner Truth.
  - Swearing in of Judge Mary C. Morgan / WCLC Opening, 24 September 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 7)
    Side 1 is a recording of the recording of the swearing in of Judge Mary Carolyn Morgan at San Francisco City Hall. Mary Morgan is a judge of the San Francisco County Superior Court and former judge of the San Francisco Municipal Court. She was the first openly lesbian judge appointed in the United States. Side 2 is a recording of the WCLC opening with Sylvia Kohan singing and Johnnie Staggs speaking and fundraising.
  - Eighteen Months Later..., 8 November 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 8)
    Forum focused on the topic of gay people in Cuba, specifically Cuban lesbian refugees. The group that organized the forum works to get lesbians out of refugee camps in the United States. Speakers explore the history of US relations with Cuba, the history of gay people in Cuba, and the experience of refugees in US. Discussion with audience also included in recording.
  - Donor Paternity Panel, 6 December 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 9)
    Panel discusses a lawsuit over donor insemination and paternity, the issue of donors' involvement in children's lives, and women's legal rights when raising children from donor insemination. Women discuss their experience having children through donor insemination.
  - Older Women's Group, [ca. 1980s]; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 10)
    Meeting of an older women's group, where participants discuss various issues with aging. Topics include: ageism, interactions with youth, older women's activities, older women in the workplace, and other women's issues.
  - On Being Gay: Homosexuality and the Church, 1973; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 11)
    Professionally produced recording of a study on homosexuality and the Church. Interviews and discussions with Phyllis Lyon, Reverend William R. Johnson, Jim & Lyndall, Dr. Herbert Vanderwoort, Attorney Walter Barnett, Reverend Ross Greek, and Dr. David Napier. recording by Thesis Creative Educational Resources.
  - Sexuality, Class, and Conflict in the Lesbian Workplace, 6 May 1983; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 12)
    Lisa Rofel and Kathleen Weston, both from Stanford, present ideas and research from their paper, Sexuality, Class, and Conflict. They examine class conflicts in the workplace within lesbians and feminists, focusing on the case study of a strike at Amazon Auto Repair-a lesbian auto repair shop. They also acknowledge that class conflict in the lesbian workplace publicizes social and private spheres, as sexual identity is clear in the workplace.
  - Yosemite Women's Music Festival: Building Coalitions, [ca. 1980s]; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 13)
    Speech by Bernice Regan at the Yosemite Women's Music Festival about racism, unity, and coalition building for women's groups. The recording aired on KPFA and was produced by Reyna Cowan.
  - Incest Discussion with Judy Freespirit, 26 January 1982; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 14)
    Recording of discussion with Judy Freespirit about incest. They discuss family relationships, therapy, emotional distress, supports groups, and other issues.
  - Bunny Mac Culloch: Mazer Archives, 1 January 1989; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 15)
    Bunny Mac Culloch discussing structure and organization of archives. Recording appears to have been done by Mac Culloch herself. She describes how the archives have been organized, her thought process during the archiving of the collections, and her hopes for the the future of the archive.
    Audio is very scratchy.
  - Choice Centered Tarot: Lesson 1, 1982; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 1-6)
    Professional recording of correspondence course on tarot. Gail Fairfield is the author of the course. Fairfield presents the tarot as a tool for personal empowerment, introspection, and making choices. She emphasizes the psychological meanings of the tarot, explaining imagery that can be applied to any deck.
  - Old Dykes' Tales, 26 March 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 7-8)
    Myths of the lesbian movement explained, including when the lesbian movement began. Discussion stems from topic of lesbian fiction, pulp, and non-fiction. Self-labeled dykes share stories of coming out, relationships, and notable events in their lives.
  - Womans Place Lockout, 19 September 1982; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 9-11)
    Meeting held at Ollie's in Oakland, California to discuss the ICI: Woman's Place Bookstore controversy. The bookstore was located in Oakland. The ICI: Woman's Place Bookstore was founded by Alice Molloy Carol Wilson. ICI is an acronym that stands for "information center incorporate." The goal of the bookstore was to incorporate different ideas having to do with women, race, and other diversities. Overtime, an internal struggle developed between members of Women's Place, resulting in a lock out four other members by Alice and Carol. The women at the meeting discuss the events that took place immediately following the literal lock out and the legal measures that have been taken. They state that the purpose of the meeting is to come to an understanding of where the disagreement stemmed from and what steps to take from that date.
  - Quaker Lesbian Affinity Group: Livermore Action, 26 June 1982; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 12)
    Recording of discussion with group of women on the events that took place during Livermore Action, including the process of being arrested by police and the experience of incarceration. Participants include: Kim Bancroft, Karen Rogers, Carol Vorlvolakos, Bettye Travis, Alexis Dees, Elizabeth Beam, Becky Fischbach, Pat Bough, Anne Branch, and Jan Zobel.
  - Lesbian school workers on Proposition 6, 1978; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 13)
    Professional recording that addresses the 1978 California initiative, Proposition 6, put on the ballot by conservative state legislator John Briggs of Fullerton that would give California school boards permission to dismiss openly gay or lesbian school workers, as well as straight school employees who openly support gay rights. The recording is an argument against Proposition 6, also known as the Briggs Initiative. Openly gay San Francisco politician Harvey Milk was active in fighting the measure, and opposition from California Governor Ronald Reagan to President Jimmy Carter helped to defeat it. Proposition 6's failure was one of the first setbacks to the 1970's anti-gay campaign lead by Anita Bryant and her organization "Save Our Children" in Dade County, Florida.
  - Lesbians in the Convent, 13 June 1982; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 14)
    Conversation between Peg Cruikshank, Rosemary Curt, and Nancy Manahan about lesbians in the convent. Meeting took place at the home of Peg Cruikshank. The discussion stems from Curt and Manahan's upcoming (at the time of recording) publishing of a collection of stories about lesbians in the convent. Topics include group meetings, reasons for joining convent, education, and need to surround self with all-women community.
  - Lesbian/Gay Archives, 28 June 1983; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 15)
    Recording of Jim Kepner giving a speech regarding Lesbian and Gay archives. Kepner discusses the importance of creating such repositories despite the concerns over strong, homophobic opposition, as well as the issue of collection development.
  - WCLC Opening Day, [ca. 1980s]; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 16)
    Recording of the WCLC opening with Sylvia Kohan singing and Johnnie Staggs speaking and fundraising. Side 2 is a recording of the recording of the swearing in of Judge Mary Carolyn Morgan at San Francisco City Hall. Mary Morgan is a judge of the San Francisco County Superior Court and former judge of the San Francisco Municipal Court. She was the first openly lesbian judge appointed in the United States. S
  - Judy Grahn: A Heart-Shaped Journey to a Similar Place, 1983; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 17)
    Judy Grahn speaks at the Sappho Lectures at the New School, and presents the essay: "A Heart-Shaped Journey to a Similar Place". The lecture examines the loss of the place where women had power with a chronology from Sappho and the island of Lesbos, through medieval times and then to women's roles in (then current) contemporary time. Grahn discusses her life and work as a writer. Judy Rae Grahn is an American poet, born July 28, 1940 in Chicago, Illinois. Grahn's work focuses on the feminist and lesbian experience.
  - Judy Grahn: Writing From a House of Women, 1983; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 18)
    Judy Grahn speaks at the Sappho Lectures at the New School, and presents the essay: "Writing from a House of Women". The lecture explores lesbian literature and the significance of writing from a lesbian identity. Grahn discusses her life and work as a writer. Judy Grahn is an American poet, born July 28, 1940 in Chicago, Illinois. Grahn's work focuses on the feminist and lesbian experience.
- Groups Alphabetized by Group/Topic Cassettes, 1975-1995; Series 19.; 59 audio cassette tapes
  Produced albums and recordings of musical groups and singers.
  - Ruth Barrett & Cyntia Smith: Aeolus, 1981; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 1)
    Ruth Barrett and Cyntia Smith are singers and songwriters, who specialize in playing the fretted dulcimer. The album music is inspired by myth, folklore, ancient symbolism, and the celebration of Nature. Their performances also include love songs, unique instrumental pieces and traditional folk music of the British Isles. Side 1: Bird on the Briar; Never Weather Beaten Saile; The Mermaid; Lullaby For Amanda; Every Woman Born; King of the Fairies; Aeolus, The Wind. Side 2: As I Roved Out, Lesson For Two Lutes, Blow The Candles Out, Pastime With Good Company, The Rolling Of the Stones, The Weary Cutters.
    Copyright 1981 Aeolus Records
  - Allegra Broughton: Original Songs Straight From The Heart, 1980; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 2)
    Allegra Broughton is a singer, song writer, and guitar player. She is also a DJ on KRCB-FM 91.1 Santa Rosa Public Radio, hosting the "Connections" Show, and is a member of the groups, Solid Air, Wild Catahoulas, Soul Joy, and The Sorentinos. Side 1: Feelin', Your Eyes Give You Away, No Love Intended, I Can't Do It, Deep River. Side 2: So Long, Touch My Heart, Stranger To You, Management Blues, Lullaby.
    Copyright 1980 SRS*
  - Darol Anger/Barbara Higbie Quintet: Live at Montreux, 19 July 1984; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 3)
    Live recording of the First Evening With Windham Hill at the Montreux Jazz Festival. Side 1: Egrets, The Lights In The Sky Are Stars, Daughter of Cups, Egypt. Side 2: In What Hour, Pumpkin Time, Duet, Near Northern.
    Copyright 1985 Windham Hill Records.
  - Blazing Redheads, 1988; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 4)
    Seven member Latin jazz band. Side 1: Paradise Drive, Cienega, Sea Level, In Search Of..., February Song. Side 2: Santa Fe, Get Down (and Stay Down), Final Segment, Mozambo, My Picasso.
    Copyright 1988 Reference Recordings
  - Ruth Barrett & Cyntia Smith: Deepening, 1984; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 5)
    Ruth Barrett and Cyntia Smith are singers and songwriters, who specialize in playing the fretted dulcimer. The album music is inspired by myth, folklore, ancient symbolism, and the celebration of Nature. Side 1: Where Only Lovers Can Go, Deepening, Dance of the Meadow Mice, Chosen Country, The Doffing Mistress, Plains of Waterloo. Side 2: Lord of the Dance, Imagine the World, Factory Girl, Song of the Wandering Aengus, The Orange Rogue, Allu Mari Mi Portati
    Copyright 1984 Aeolus Music
  - Alix Dobkin: Lavender Jane Loves Women, 1973; audio cassette tape (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 6)